Guide to the Rice University ROTC Committee records, 1941-1983 UA 171
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas
Rice University ROTC Committee records
1941-1983
Woodson Research Center, Rice University, Houston, Texas https://library.rice.edu/woodson
Rice University
UA 171
6 Linear Feet (6 boxes)
These records contain information on commissions, minutes of meetings both of the committee and of the Association of Naval ROTC Colleges; questionnaires sent to other schools with ROTC programs; information on various ROTC summer camp programs and a significant number of correspondences between ROTC Committee chairmen, faculty, and administration.
Biographical Note
The Rice University Naval ROTC program is a part of the Houston Consortium, with a sister program at Prarie View A&M. The Rice Naval ROTC unit serves Rice University, University of Houston, Texas Southern University, and Houston Baptist University. The Rice Naval ROTC unit is realtively small with around only forty members, but it is known for being an elite, well-run unit, whose purpose historically has been the training of nuclear power officers for submarine and surface vessels.
The Houston Consortium is comprised of one company of three platoons, and its goal is to prepare students for careers as officers in the United States Navy and United States Marine Corps. It is led by Captain Jeffrey K. Gruetzmacher, a United States Navy Commanding Officer (Aviator) and Lieutenant Colonel Stuart R. Lockhart, a United States Marine Corps Executive Officer (Infantry). The Rice Unit is led by Captain Eric S. Christophe, USMC, Lieutenant James H. Kepper, US Navy, and Lieutenant (Junior Grade) Jason A. Fite, US Navy.
Scope and Contents
These records contain information on commissions, minutes of meetings both of the committee and of the Association of Naval ROTC Colleges; questionnaires sent to other schools with ROTC programs; information on various ROTC summer camp programs and a significant number of correspondences between ROTC Committee chairmen, faculty, and administration.
Access Restrictions
This material is open for research.
Conditions Governing Access
Stored off-site at the Library Service Center. Please request this material via woodson@rice.edu or call 713-348-2586.
Acquisition Information
This material was transferred to the Woodson Research Center in 1973 and circa 1990.
Index Terms
Subjects
Universities and colleges; Military
Document Types
minutes (administrative records); letters (correspondence)
Places
Rice University
Subjects (Corporations)
United States. Naval Reserve Officers Training Corps
- Series I: 1941-1969, 119180
  - NROTC: Unit establishment, scholarship applications, notices, orders, corresp., 1941, 1947-49, 119181 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, notices, scholarship applications, corresp., 1948-50, 119182 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - NROTC: Agenda, corresp., 1949-50, 119183 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - NROTC: Corresp., memos, reports, awards, minutes, 1950-51, 119184 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Navy Committee ROTC survey, 1951, 119185 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - NROTC: Scholarship applications, corresp., reports, memos, 1951-52, 119186 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - ROTC: Corresp., memos, reports, curriculum info., 1952-53, 119187 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Death of Rice NROTC members, 1953, 119188 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - NROTC: Jesse Jones Scholarships, 1953, 119189 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NRTOC: Jesse Jones Scholarships, 1954-55, 119190 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Awards, minutes, reports, corresp., 1954-55, 119191 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Scholarships, reports, corresp., 1956, 119192 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Reports, corresp., curriculum, minutes, 1957, 119193 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., minutes, reports, directives, 1958, 119194 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Corresp., minutes, 1961-62, 119195 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Association of NRTOC Colleges minutes, 1963-64, 1963-1964; 119196 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., minutes, reports, 1963-64, 119197 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., unit establishment, 1965, 119198 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Association of NROTC Colleges minutes, 1965, 119199 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Commissions, reports, 1965-69, 119200 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - History, curriculum, reports, 1965-69, 119201 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Corresp., memos, scholarships, 1966, 119202 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Association of NROTC Colleges minutes, 1966, 119203 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., curriculum, 1967, 119204 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Association of NROTC Colleges minutes, 1967, 119205 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Corresp., memos, curriculum, new facility, 1968, 119206 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Association of NROTC Colleges minutes, 1968, 119207 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - NROTC Association reports, Dec. 1968, 119208 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Association of NROTC Colleges reports, 1968-70, 119209 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - ROTC Coordinating Committee Enrichment Program, 1969, 119210 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Corresp., memos, reports, minutes, 1969, 119211 (Box 5, Folder 1)
- Series II: 1970-1983, 119212
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., reports, minutes, history of Rice AROTC, Jan-June 1970, 119213 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., July-Dec. 1970, 119214 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Association of NROTC Colleges minutes, 1970, 119215 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Corresp., memos, questionnaires, Jan-April 1971, 119216 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Corresp., memos, scholarships, Rice unit brochure, May-Aug. 1971, 119217 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Corresp., memos, appointments, Sept.-Dec. 1971, 119218 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., commissions, Jan-May 1972, 119219 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., unit brochure, June-Dec. 1972, 119220 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Association of NROTC Colleges minutes, 1972, 119221 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., appointments, 1973, 119222 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Replies to questionnaires, 1973, 119223 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., 1974-75, 119224 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., 1976-80, 119225 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - NROTC/ROTC: Memos, corresp., members, 1981-83, 119226 (Box 6, Folder 7)